Mss.Ms.Coll.123
American Philosophical Society
Dorothy Nelkin papers
Circa 1970-2002
Mss.Ms.Coll.123
American Philosophical Society
69.0 Linear feet
Dorothy Wolfers Nelkins (1933-2003), sociologist and science policy educator, documented the often uneasy relationship between science and the public, as the author or co-author of 26 books and numerous published articles. Educated at Cornell, her research centered on both how science was viewed by the public and how it was presented in the media. After her career at Cornell (1963-89), she became a distinguished NYU Professor in the Dept. of Sociology and an affiliated Professor at the School of Law there (1990-2003). Nelkins wrote about disputes over genetically-modified organisms, public responses to genetic manipulation, the implications of industry-university relationships and artists’ responses to the genetic revolution. Some of her most significant works include Selling Science: How the Press Covers Science and Technology (1987); Dangerious Diagnostics: the Social Power of Biological Information (1989), The DNA Mystique: The Gene as a Cultural Icon (1995) and Body Bazaar: The Market for Human Tissue in the Biotechnology Age (2001).
Nelkin, Dorothy
Box 1-28
Biographical/Historical note
Sociologist Dorothy Nelkin specialized in the relationship between science and society.
Arrangement note
Series I – Correspondence (.5 linear foot) Series II – Research/Subject materials (8 linear feet) Series III- Works by Nelkins (7 linear feet)- Series IV- Works by others (2 linear feet) –Series V Conferences and Committees (2 linear feet) – Series VI- Court cases (0.75 linear feet) – Series VII-Personal Series-(0 .25 linear feet)-Series VIII- Printed Material - cartoons. Clippings? Dot’s published works? Her library? –Series IX –Ephemera-(0.25 linear feet)-Non-textual formats: Series X – Photos (2 folders) – Series XI-Computer disks.
Scope and Contents note
Collection Overview
Collection Overview: Correspondence Series I consists of Dorothy Nelkin’s correspondence with various colleagues and scholars over the course of her entire professional life, as well as correspondence with publishers and co-authors. Of particular interest is her correspondence with, of the Human Genome Project. There are four letters to _____from Nelkin and some of Nelkin’s responses. The bulk of the correspondence is incoming. Correspondence with Publishers: is comprised of Nelkin’s correspondence with the many publisherss he worked with in over __ years of writing. The chief correspondents are Lori Andrews...
Works By Series III consists of works by Dorothy Nelkin, related notes, and correspondence; reviews of individual works are also included. It contains complete book manuscripts, as well as journal and popular magazine articles. Much of the series is comprised of undated manuscripts of both published and unpublished articles, typewritten by Nelkin. Also included are course materials from classes she taught at Cornell and NYU. Book reviews written by Nelkin are included,. authored by Nelkin are also included, which highlight the diversity of her interests and abilities. Speaking engagements/Lectures/Lectures notes [COURSE MATERIALS?????] Cornell/NYU:
Series V is made up of material from Nelkins work while at Cornell and NYU. Nelkin served many years as a professor/lecturer and later as a Visiting Scholar at…. The series consists of class materials, student evaluations, and correspondence to and from the University, ….
Works by Others
Series VI is comprised of works by others, and greatly reflects Nelkin’s varied research interests: racial and social equality, women’s rights, child development, humanistic psychology and genetics. Such interests are represented by the works of many influential people in the aforementioned fields, such as ______and many others. Although Nelkin remained well read in the works of those authors she did not always agree with, especially the racial and eugenic theories of authors such as ____. So while the series does not accurately reflect the entirety of Nelkin’s opinions, it is a great resource for discovering the topics she returned to again and again. Topics of interest. DNA; obtaining unauthorized tissue samples/treatment of bodies….cord blood, animal rights/cloning; science of race; law and cloning; surveillance (data storing microchips) Includes a number of reviews of works by Nelkin by other authors.
Committees and Organizations Series VII consists of material relating to the various committees and organizations in which Nelkin participated. From ___ to ___, Nelkin AAAS Committee on Scientific Freedom and Responsibility, serving as chair of its Subcommittee on Intellectual Property…..served on the AAAS Board of Directors, 1983-7….as the chairperson and consequently much of this series consists of material….AAAS committee on Science, Technology and Public Policy, Also [prevalent] represented is material relating to the American Bar Association, NYU Institute for the Humanities; NY Bar Association, Committee on Bioethical Issues. a number of ____ and _____groups.
Certificates and awards Series VIII contains certificates and awards received by Ashley Montagu. A majority of the series dates to the 1990s, and is largely made up of lifetime achievement awards. Personal Information: Series IX, the Personal Information series is composed of several versions of Nelkin’s curriculum vitae, a letter of appointment? This series also includes a Xerox of her _____ passport, personal financial documents, among other ephemera. Certificate???
Printed Materials Series X, the printed materials series, consists of published works and reprints authored mainly by others, but includes many works by herself. Also included are bound volumes, magazines and newsletters, as well as trial transcripts from the_______ case, for which Nelkin was deposed.
Photographs Series XI consists of photographs. Two folders; Folder 1 includes photos for her mss. Of Workers at Risk: Voices from the Workplace. (1984). Folder 2 includes a portrait of Dorothy for use in publications and a personal candid? photo of Nelkin and ______ Series XI also contains photos removed from correspondence for conservation purposes,
Computer disks Series XI consists of versions of her published works, including Body Bazaar and The Business of Bodies, as well as several unlabelled disks.
Bibliography-Selected publications
On the Season: Aspects of the Migrant Labor System (1970). New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations, Cornell University. The University and Military Research: Moral Politics at MIT (1972). Cornell University Press. Jetport: The Boston Airport Controversy (1975). Transaction Books 1977a. Technological Decisions and Democracy. Beverly Hills, Calif.: Sage. 1977b. "Technology and Public Policy." In Science, Technology and Society: A Cross-Disciplinary Perspective, ed. I. Spiegel-Rosing and D. de Solla Price, pp. 393-442. London: Sage. 1979 Controversy: Politics of Technical Decisions. Beverly Hills: Sage. Science Textbook Controversies and the Politics of Equal Time (1977). MIT Press. The Atom Besieged: Extra-Parliamentary Dissent in France and Germany (with Michael Pollak; 1981). MIT Press. The Creation Controversy: Science or Scripture in the Schools (1982). New York: W.W. Norton. Science as Intellectual Property, 1983. Workers at Risk: Voices from the workplace (with M.S. Brown; 1984). Chicago: University of Chicago Press. The Language of Risk: Conflicting Perspectives in Occupational Health (1985). SAGE Publications. Selling Science: How the press covers science and technology (1987). W.H., Freeman Press. Translated into Japanese and Spanish. 2nd ed., 1995. Dangerous Diagnostics: The Social Power of Biological Information (1989). New York: Basic. 2nd ed. 1994. A Disease of Society: The Cultural Response to AIDS (with D. Willis, eds.; 1991). Cambridge U. Press. The Animal Rights Crusade, 1991. Controversy: Politics of Technical Decision, 3d ed., 1992. The DNA Mystique: The Gene as Cultural Icon, 1995. The Body Bazaar: The Market for Human (or Body?) Tissue in the Biotechnology (2001). Age Crown Books. Translated into Korean, Chinese, Japanese, and Italian. The Molecular Gaze (with Suzanne Anker; 2003). Cold Spring Harbor Press. http://depts.washington.edu/hssexec/newsletter/1997/nelkin.html (Science, Technology and Public Policy)
- Correspondence, 1969-2002
  - Cornell
    - Cornell appointment information, 1969-1986
    - Documents and job offers, 1972-1985
    - Guggenheim, 1983-1985
    - Winterhalder, 1977
  - General
    - London, 2002
    - Lori Andrews, 1997-1999
    - Lori Andews, Legal, 2000
    - New Conformity-Contract, 1988-1989
    - Resolve, 1989-1994
    - Selling Science, 1987
    - Von Eckardt, n.d.
  - New York University
    - Annual reports, 1991-1995
    - Biotechnology Study Center, 2000
    - Caplan/Speranza, 2001-2002
    - STS Colloquium Series, 1989-1992
    - Draper Program, 1997-1998
    - Faculty orientation packet, 2000
    - Grant applications, 1993-1994
    - Bruce V. Lewenstein, 1989-1998
    - Lisette (Lisa) Fuhs Mallary, 1992
    - Miscellaneous, 1986-1999
    - Miscellaneous, 1989-2002
    - Miscellaneous, 1991-1999
    - Gisli Palsson, 1999-2000
    - Mary Poovey, 1997-1998
    - NYU Press, 1998
    - Nicholas Rose, 1998
    - Charles E. Rosenberg, 1972 reprint?
    - Russell Sage College, 1995-1996
    - Society of Fellows, 1998-2001
    - Stephen Epstein-Promotion Recommendation, 1997
- Research
  - Tissue Banks, Bulk, 1994; 1992-1994
- Works by Nelkin
  - AIDS and the Social Contract: Comments for NYU AIDS Panel, 1987-1994; Also includes typed mss. & published version (Autumn 1988)of "Placing Blame for Devastating Disease," with Sander L. Gilman and published (1987 in Reviews of Infectious Diseases) version of "AIDS and the Social Sciences: Review of Useful Knowledge and Research Needs. Permission form for Placing Blame abstract (1988) and typed 2 p. mss. of "Lecture for Theory and Culture."; Gilman, Sander L.
  - Biological Testing and The Management of Workplace Risks (draft), 2/26/90
  - Biotechnology and the public: animal patenting disputes, May 28, 1992; Contains p. 1 of "Communicating biotechnology: statement;" a "biographical statement" ALSO contains: 2 copies of "Science and hunger: the problematic promises of a technological fix" (dated 4/11/95
  - The Case of Silicone Breast Implants, 1996
  - Changing Dimensions of the Scientific Movement (April 1978), 1976-1978
  - Conflict Resolution in Technological Disputes, May 8, 1978
  - Consensus et Reglement des Conflicts: la Politique de l'Evaluation des Risques, 1-3 avril 1979
  - Controversies and the Authority of Science, Possibly after 1987
  - Covering Medical Technology, 1988-1989
  - Cultural Perspectives on Blood (Final draft), Jan. 20, 1997; Includes earlier version from 1996 and research notes/summaries
  - Dangerous Diagnositics-General Introduction, n.d.
  - Data Ownership and Access to Research: Issues of the 1990's
  - Diet and Cancer: The Politics of Risk Communication, 1987
  - A Disease of Soceity: Cultural Impact of Aids, 1/8/90; Includes a University of Cambridge Press Memorandum of Agreement, date Julyl 9, 1990
  - Environmental and consumer movements in the United States, April 14, 1980
  - Environmental politics: the detergent ban in Suffolk County: a seminar project for the Cornell Program on Science, Technology and Society, undated (1971 or later?)
  - Ethical Conflicts in Occupational Medicine, 1984-85?
  - The Ethics of Discovery, May 2, 1994-July 18, 1995; THe Ethics of Discover and three letters: 1) From Robert N. Ubell of Scientific American (May 2, 1994); 2) From Juis Gonzalez of Scientific American (June 19, 1995) and 3) From Dorothy to both Bob Ubell and Luis Gonzales (July 18, 1995
  - The Environmental and Consumer Movements in the United States, 1980-1981
  - For the Individual, the Double Helix has a Double Edge, June 13, 2002; Includes email correspondence [5/7 & 5/20/2002] to Nelkin from Carina Dennis (; from Nelkin [6/10/2002] original folder includes mss. notes; Dennis, Carina
  - Forbidden Research: Limits to Inquiry in the Social Sciences, 1980
  - Fraud in Biomedical Research (two versions), n.d.
  - The Gene in the Popular Culture Media, 2000-2001
  - Genetic Predisposition: An Ideological Construct, August 25, 1994, 2001; Includes: 1) published chapter: "The Politics of Predisposition. The Social Meaning of Predictive Biology 2)Photocopy of Genetic Predisposition and the Politics of Prediction a chapter (?) from "New Dimensions in Bioethics: Science, Ethics and the Formulation of Public Policy (2001) 3) Typed mss. of "Freeman Presention" (undated)
  - Genetic Screening in the Workplace (draft), 11/29/90
  - Genetic Screening: What it Means for Health and Ethics in the Future, 1996
  - Genetics and Family Relationships, October 26-November 2, 1994; Also includes photocopies of 2 letters from Nelkin to Katherine Legg, [from Spence Chapin] dated Oct. 26 & Nov. 2, 1994 respectively. A page of typed "notes from Eppler, Oct 26, 1996 [should be 94...] and 2 brochures about adoption--one from Spence Chapin and a photocpied section from theEncyc. of Assns, entitled "Social Welfare Organizations."
  - Genetics and Society: Social and Ethical Implications, Jan. 11-Nov. 6, 1995
  - The Genetics of Human Behavior: Representations in Popular Culture, Dec 14, 16, 1994; Also contains typed, unsigned letter from Nelkin to "Jon."
  - Genome: The Social Power of Biological Tests, 4/1/90 & August 22 (no year)
  - The High Cost of Hype: Space Shuttle Reporting Before and After the Challenger (Susan Lindee with Nelkin), 1985-6?
  - Images of Science in the American Press, 1/28/91
  - Implementing the Right to Environmental Protection: Public Participation, 1982
  - The Laetrile Dispute: Science and Technology in the Pits (Commentary), 1979
  - Limits to Scientific Inquiry: Some Issues Raised by the Recombinant DNA Dispute, 1978?
  - Managing Biomedical News (Published in Social Research), 1985-1986
  - The Metalite of the Animal Rights Movement: Sentimental Anthropomorphism and the Critique of Instrumentalism with James M. Jasper (draft), 1990-1991
  - The New Biology and Social Control, n.d.--1990? (1985 quoted)
  - New Diagnostic Technologies and the Culture of the Test, 2/6/1989-Sept 26, 1994; Includes: 1) "Social Impact of Genetic Screening" (3/8/89: "Lect\harvard") 2) General Introduction (from Dangerous Diagnostics) undated 3)1 p. The Human Genone Project: Ethical and Social Issues--Legal Issues (Dec 17, 1990/The Salk Institute) 4) 2 pg. published w/ photos of Nelkin entitled "Dangers of the American Mania for Genetic Testing: Bonnar Day 1990 5) typed mss. of "The Cultural Context of Genetic Testing" (HUGO Sept 12-94); Tancredi, Laurence R.
  - Observations from My Research, 1993-1994
  - The Political Evolution of the Anti-Nuclear Movement in the United States, 1978
  - The Politics of Personhood (Program on ST&S), 1982-1983
  - Popular Images of the Atom and the Fear of Risk (6 papers), 1985-1990
  - Promotional metaphors and their popular appeal, April 15, 1993; loose: 1 p. of mss. notes and a xerox letter from Jane K. Bulleid
  - Prediction and the public meaning of science, 3/15/1992; Includes program from the NYU Graduate School of Arts & Science Convocation, May 13, 1992 (Cargengie Hall, NYC)
  - The Pro-Nuclear Movement, 1978-1980
  - Propriety and Property: The Tissue Market Meets the Courts, 1999-2002
  - Protest as Participation: The Significance of the Antinuclear Movement, 1981
  - Science and hunger: the problematic promises of a technological fix, 4/11/1995; In folder labelled: Biotechnology and the public: animal patenting disputes; 2 copies, one with extensive notes
  - Science and Technology Policy and the Democratic Process, n.d--1977?
  - Science and the Press (5 papers), 1984-1988
  - Science as Intellectural Property Revisited, 1986-1987
  - Science, Technologie et Democratie, 1978-1983
  - Scientific Knowledge, Public Policy and Democracy: A Review Essay, 1978-1979
  - Scientific Rationality and Political Ideology, 1976-1977
  - Scientists and [the] Public: The Experience of Ecologists, June, 1975
  - Selling Science: Scientists in Search of a Press, 1990
  - So What's Funny About the Energy Crisis?, 1975
  - Social Dynamics of Genetic Testing: the Case of Fragile-X, March 6, 1995; Earlier version of paper dated May 24, 1994- and The Cultural Context of Genetic Testing (Sept. 9, 1994)
  - The Social Functions of Humor, 1974?
  - Social Impact of Genetic Screening, 1989
  - The Social Meaning of Biological Tests, 1989
  - The Tissue in the Body: Legal Disputes and Social Meanings (w/ Lori Andrews), 1996? (bibliography mentions forthcoming, 1997)
  - Reviews/Proposal reviews, 1992
  - Risk (4 papers), 1984
  - The New Diagnostics and the Power of Biologic Information, with Laurence Trancredi, 1989
  - Reviews by Nelkin
    - Controlling Our Destinies, 2000
      Sloan, Phillip R.
    - Directing Technology, June 7, 1979
      Johnston, Ron
    - Do Autobiographies Illuminate the Scientific Enterprise?, March/April 1984; Includes a letter to Nelkin from Richard Magat, 1/25/1984
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes a letter to Nelkin from Richard Magat, 1/25/1984.
      General note
      Published in Foundation News, March/April 1984, pp. 77-78
      Bruner, Jerome S. (Jerome Seymour), 1915-; Casimir, Hendrick; Medawar, Peter, Sir; Thomas, Lewis
    - Misc., Sept. 15, 18, 2000; Correspondence about Public Concerns about 'The Gift of Life'"; mss. is missing
      Includes two letters to Nelkin: 1) from David B. McCurdy (Senior Editor, Second Opinion)[9/18/2000]; 2) from Therese L. Samodral [9/15/2000]
      Samodral, Therese L.
    - New Genetics and the Public's Health, Jan 1, 2003
      Bunton, Robin; Petersen, Alan
    - Politics of Heredity, The, undated, 1985 & 1991; Includes 2 articles: 1) by Diane B. Paul (1985?); 2) by Philip J. Pauly (1991)
      Paul, Diane B.
    - Royal Society--Proposal Reviews, July 1, 1992; Includes correspondence to and from Nelkin
      Includes correspondence to and from Nelkin; Correspondents include Dr. P.M.D. Collin, Director, SEPSU [Science and Engineering Policy Unit, Royal Society]; Dr. Mairead O'Driscoll (6/11/92); Barbara Drillsma, Assn. of British Science Writers (43/4/93)
    - America By Design: Science, Technology and the Rise of Corporate Capitalism, Jan/Feb 1978
      Noble, David F.
- Works by Others
  - Lori Andrews
- Conferences and Committees, 1974-2001
  - Academic Medicine Development Company, Bioethics Advisory Group, 2001
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, March 24-July 8, 1987
  - American Assn. for the Advancement of Science
    - Annual meetings, 1984-1995
    - Eugenics, 1996?
    - Lectures, 1986
    - Symposiums, 1979-1995
    - Workshop-Ethics, n.d.
    - American Bar Association, 1981-1982
      - ABA Section of Administrative Law & Regulatory Practice, 1997
  - APSA (American Political Science Assn.?), 1974-1975
  - Ares-Serono Symposia-4th Conference on Research Policies and Quality Assurance "Public Perceptions", 1995
  - The Aspen Institute, n.d.- 1994
  - Brooklyn Law School (Symposium), Feb 9-March 9, 2001
  - Center for Global Parnership (Workshop), 1995-1997
  - The Ciba Foundation, 1986
  - City University of NY, Center on Violence and Human Survival, 1990
  - City University of NY, Center for Lesbian and Gay Studies (Symposium), 1991
  - Columbia University Lionel Trilling Seminars, Oct. 16-Nov. 9, 1989
  - DNA Files (Genome Radio Project), 1997-2001
  - Foundation for American Communications, 1989-1990
    - FACS: Science, Pseudoscience and Quackery: Knowing the Difference, a Science Issues Conference for Journalists, July 20-Sept. 25, 1988
  - George Washington University, Center for Health Policy Research/Workshop, 1993
  - Los Alamos National Laboratory, 1994
  - Max-Planck-Institut fur Wissenschaftsgeschichte, 1997-1998
  - Miscellaneous Conferences, Workshops, Etc., 1986-1998
  - Miscellaneous Editorial Boards, 1993-2001
  - National Academy of Sciences, Institute of Medicine--Misc., 1986-1994
  - National Academy of Sciences, Institute of Medicine Miscellaneous, 1986-1994
  - National Advisory Council for Human Genome Research, 1991
  - National Agricultural Biotechnology Council?, 1992
  - National Bioethics Advisory Commission, 1999-2000
  - National Center for Genome Resources, 1996
  - National Commission on the Future of DNA Evidence, Working Group on Legal Issues, 1998-1999
    - Legal Issues Working Group-- 3 floppy disks; Correspondence, Memos, 1996-1999
    - Legal Issues Working Group--reports, research, 1999-2000
  - National Institutes of Health, 1992-1997
    - NIH-DOE ELSI Working Group, 1992
      - Correspondence
      - NIH Miscellaneous, 1991-1994
    - NIH Human Embryo Research Panel, 1993-1994
    - Miscellaneous, 1991-1994
    - NIH-DOE Joint Working Group on the Ethical, Legal and Social Implications of Human Genome Research, 1995-1996
  - National Science Foundation, 1978
  - New York Academy of Medicine, Center for Urban Bioethics (Advisory Group), 1998-2001
  - New York Academy of Medicine/Human Genome Project Conference, 1990-1991
  - NY Academy of Sciences, 1993-1998
    - Scientific Responsibility in the Biosciences (Conference), Jan 15, 1998
    - International Conference on Science and Technology Policy, 1979
  - New York Science Polity Association, 1988
  - New York University Miscellaneous Collquia, Forums, etc., 1993-1996
  - Society for Literature and Science, 1991
  - Society for Social Studies of Science (4S) Annual Meetings (Papers), 1977-1984
  - SUNY, NY Area French History Seminar
  - Superman (television series), 1992-1993
  - Unidentified Symposia, Colloquia, etc., 1987-1996
  - Universita degli Studi de Siena/Legal Regulation of Bioethics International Workshop, 1994
  - University of CA, Berkeley, Human Rights Center, 2001-2002
  - University of Michigan, Historical Center for the Health Sciences, National Advisory Board, 2001-2002
  - University of Washington, GSPA/Dael Wolfle Lecture, Oct 1994
  - World Encyclopedia of the Cultural History of Medicine--Editorial Board, 2001
  - Yale University, Samuel F. B. Morse College (Symposium Panelist), 1987
  - Women's Media Initiative, Advisory Board, 1997
  - Straight Ahead Pictures---Tomorrow's Children, 1994-1995
- Court cases, 1977-1994
- Personal, 1989-2002
- Printed mateials
- Ephemera
  - Cartoons
- Photos
- Computer disks